Guide to the Lindsey and Brown Photographs, circa 1890
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lindsey and Brown photographs circa 1890
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lindsey and Brown
2.0 linear feet Extent: 53 Items
Photographers of Asheville, NC. Photographs (chiefly cabinet cards produced by Lindsey and Brown) of street scenes, landscapes, and tourist attractions in late 19th-century western N.C. Descriptive text is printed on the reverse side of many of the photographs. Most photographs were taken in the vicinity of the Swannanoa, Hot Springs, the French Broad River, Round Knob, Hickory Nut Gap, Buck Forest, Highlands, and Asheville. Contains photographs of the Battery Park Hotel, Chimney Rock, Hooker's Mill, McElroy Tunnel, Devil's Pulpit, Paint Rock, the Seven Sisters, the Swannanoa tunnel stockade, the Murphy Division, Devil's Slip Gap, the Western North Carolina Railroad and U.S. Mail boys. Includes several images of African Americans in western N.C. Collection also includes 4 photographs produced by Brown alone and 3 stereoscopic views produced by Nat W. Taylor.
RL.00817
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lindsey and Brown Photographs were received by the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library as a purchase in 1997.
Biographical and Historical Note
Thomas H. Lindsey (1849-1927) was born in Virginia and moved to Tennessee by the 1870s, where he did photography work. He and his family moved to Asheville, NC in 1888, where he started the city's leading commercial photography studio. Edward E. Brown (c. 1858-1934), a photographer from Ohio, established himself in Asheville in 1886. By 1890, Lindsey and Brown had formed a partnership. They produced portraits and photographs of Asheville and the surrounding countryside at their South East Court Place studio. Their firm sold albumen print cabinet cards to the public and offered their photography services to railroads, civil engineers, and real estate agents. Lindsey and Brown's partnership dissolved by the mid-1890s, and both operated separate studios in Asheville. Lindsey continued working in photography until his retirement; Brown later became a successful florist.
Collection Overview
Collection contains photographs (chiefly cabinet cards produced by Lindsey and Brown) of street scenes, landscapes, and tourist attractions in late 19th-century western N.C. Descriptive text is printed on the reverse side of many of the photographs. Most photographs were taken in the vicinity of the Swannanoa, Hot Springs, the French Broad River, Round Knob, Hickory Nut Gap, Buck Forest, Highlands, and Asheville. Contains photographs of the Battery Park Hotel, Chimney Rock, Hooker's Mill, McElroy Tunnel, Devil's Pulpit, Paint Rock, the Seven Sisters, the Swannanoa tunnel stockade, the Murphy Division, Devil's Slip Gap, the Western North Carolina Railroad and U.S. Mail boys. Includes several images of African Americans in western N.C. Collection also includes 4 photographs produced by Brown alone and 3 stereoscopic views produced by Nat W. Taylor. The photographs are sorted by class and the photograph number is given, if known.
Subject Headings
Taylor, Nat W.; Western North Carolina Railroad Company; African Americans -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; Photographers -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; Railroads -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; North Carolina -- Pictorial works; Photographs -- North Carolina; Cabinet photographs; Stereographs
Contents of Collection
- Photographs, circa 1890, (2 boxes)
  - Class A: Asheville and Vicinity, (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - 114: Battery Park Hotel (Box 1)
  - Class B: Beauties of the Swannanoa, (1 folder)
    - 320: Boating (Box 1)
    - River Scene (Box 1)
  - Class C: Beauties of the French Broad River, (1 folder)
    - 414a: Mountain Island (Box 1)
    - 425: Devil's Pulpit (Box 1)
    - 430: Seven Sisters (Box 1)
    - 435: French Broad River (Box 1)
    - 441: Paint Rock (Box 1)
  - Class D: Round Knob and Vicinity
    - 606: Hotel and Fountain at Round Knob (Box 1)
    - 615: McElroy Tunnel, length 89 ft. (Box 1)
    - 622: Glacial (Box 1)
    - 624: The Fountain in Winter (Box 1)
    - 633: Viaduct and Fountain (Box 1)
  - Class F: Hot Springs and Vicinity, (1 folder)
    - 552: Hotel (Box 1)
    - 560: Peter's Rock (Box 1)
    - 563: Triple Cascades, (2 photos) (Box 1)
  - Class K: Miscellaneous, (1 folder)
    - Section 1: Hickory Nut Gap and Vicinity
      - 701: Chimney Rock (Box 1)
      - 716: Chimney Rock and Hickory Nut Falls (Box 1)
    - Section 2: Buck Forest and Vicinity
      - 812: Upper Cascades (Box 1)
      - 815: Hooker's Mill (Box 1)
    - Section 5: Highlands
      - 879: U.S. Mail Boys (Box 1)
      - Unidentified photographs, (2 photographs) (Box 1)
  - Class Z: Character and Comic, (1 folder)
    - 1003: Uncle Tom's Cabin (Box 1)
    - 1004: Old Cabin Home (Box 1)
    - 1012: Cheating the Calf (Box 1)
    - 1018: White Man's Bar (Box 1)
    - 1033: A Sunbath (Box 1)
    - 1037: The Tourists (Box 1)
    - 1044: Compulsory (Box 1)
    - 1045: Stripes but no Stars (Box 1)
  - Opening of Lake Shore Avenue, (1 folder) (Box 2)
    - 6 photos (3 originals, 3 duplicates) (Box 2)
  - Western North Carolina Views, (2 folders)
    - 2 photos (1 original, 1 duplicate) (Box 2)
    - Biltmore House (2 photos) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - 12 photos (Box 2)